### PRATEEK TRIPATHI

Flat No. 32, The Picture House, Cheapside, Reading, Berkshire – RG1 7AJ 07931340769 • <a href="mailto:tripathiprateek@gmail.com">tripathiprateek@gmail.com</a> https://www.linkedin.com/in/prateek-t-4283501/

## **OBJECTIVE**

Customer-centric, result-oriented and hard-working professional with over fifteen years of experience in architecture, delivery, management and presales roles with a variety of companies from start-up to enterprises. Looking for a challenging role, one which will make the best use of my existing skills and experience and also further my development.

## **KEY TECHNICAL SKILLS**

- Container/IaC Technologies Dockers, Teraform and Kubernetes
- Cloud technologies Openstack , AWS and Google Cloud Platform
- DevOps technologies Jenkins, Ansible, Redmine, Gerrit, Git, Robot framework etc.
- SDN/NFV Technologies Juniper CSO, Nokia Nuage, understanding of MANO standards
- Virtualization software VMWare ESXi,vSphere, KVM/QEmu and Xen
- Coding Languages Python, TCL, iTCL, JaCL, Java and Expect
- Good understanding of basic networking concepts
- Good understanding of SAFe Agile concepts

## **ROLES & RESPONSIBILITIES**

- Facilitating stakeholder workshops, leading discussions and gaining consensus views on decisions
- Assessment of Product requirements & business use cases and assessment of impact analysis
- IT requirements backlog creation for proof of concept/customer trail/New Product Development
- Publishing high-level design documents and creating solution blueprint for detailed IT landscape
- Interlocking with BA/Pre-sales community on operating model, high-level design, solution fitment analysis and RFI/RFP work
- Solution presentation to senior management and stakeholders
- Working with sales to help them with technical pre-sales activities like Demo and PoC's.
- Organize internal workshops to provide technical insights to the various team for the development of high-level documents

## **EXPERIENCE**

Solution Architect, Vodafone Group (via Tata Consultancy Services), Newbury, UK Nov 2016 – June 2019

## **Responsibilities**:

- Worked primarily as Solution architect, but also played sudo technical architect for Juniper SDWAN.
- Collaborate with Product Management in aligning teams to a shared technical direction towards the accomplishment of the vision and roadmap
- Define Solution context to describe the way the solution fits the deployment environment
- Provided IIA and Blueprinting of SD-WAN offering
- Solution designed included IT stack integration with Juniper CSO REST API's, Single sign-on between Portals, Realtime change update using messaging queues, Reporting solution, etc.
- Participate in program Increment planning, to provide a general view of the solution and identify dependencies between Features, Support SMEs in Feature sizing and cost estimation of Feature acceptance criteria Review
- Feature assessment for level of design required, RAID, feature familiarization with the Feature team
- Ensure compliance against strategy and architectural scalability
- Produce L1-L4 designs as per SAFe framework (as applicable)

- Collaborate with Technical architects and SMEs to resolve design impediments during feature development
- Worked with Amdocs and Nokia to understand their product offering. Also did a PoC/Trial handover and signoff from these vendors.
- Provided technical and solution inputs related to SDN/NFV technologies.
- Participated and provided inputs on adopting SAFe agile framework for the current engagement.
- Advocating the need for adopting the DevOps model from the beginning of the program and how it can fit in the overall program.

Consultant, Cisco Systems (via Tata Consultancy Services), Gurgaon, India Mar 2011 – Oct 2016

## Responsibilities:

- Played multiple roles and wore different hats from developer, project lead to technical presales.
- Did client management and pre-sales for multiple teams and on latest technologies like Clouds, Containers and Devops.
- Deployed and managed Cisco UCS Lab for team with 60 different UCS servers and some Nexus switches.
- Deployed and managed Openstack based Dev,QA and PoC environments and mentored team members on how to manage these environments.
- Introduced DevOps and BDD process in the projects.
- Developed Nagios python plugin for Cisco UCS products.(<u>UCS</u> and <u>IMC</u> Plugins)
- Designed and helped the team on integrating OpenStack horizon UI with CISCO UCS.
- Helped team with RnD project on validation of Ironic plugins of CISCO UCS
- Created customized cloud image for various environment to suit the needs of my Dev and QA teams for there quick deployment and testing of the products.
- Used containers as primary deployment targets for building & testing products
- Use of Ansible to automate and deploy the complete solution in OpenStack.
- Framework building using open source tools like Redmine, Gerrit, Jenkins, Dockers, MySQL, and HTML5
- Managed a team of 50 to 60 team members which required me to mentor and guide team with their deliveries.
- Developed working demo and PoC for our clients on uCPE deployment

Senior Technical Lead, Gale Technologies (Now a Dell Inc. company), Noida, India Dec 2003 – Feb 2011

# Responsibilities:

- Responsible for onsite customer requirement analysis/gathering.
- Performed "Proof-of-concept" and executed pilot implementation for various customers of the company.
- Developed Device Integration libraries to communicate with end devices and virtual cloud servers.
- Worked on various product modules specifically on Eclipse-based product client and have developed various eclipse plug-ins for customers.
- Creating device integrations to enable the automation framework to interact with the devices easily
- Analyzing the automation requirement for different customers and vendors
- Providing test automation and testing cycle solutions based on existing processes / testing practices being followed at the customer site
- Analysis and development of custom tools and application required for test case automation.

# Network Engineer, Logicsoft International Pvt Ltd., New Delhi, India May 2003 – Nov 2003

## Responsibilities:

- Maintaining & troubleshooting Corporate IT servers for NTPC, Ministry of Petroleum, National Informatics center and All India Institute of Medical Sciences.
- Auditing and maintaining networks of APEDA (Govt food ministry) and MoS Petroleum.
- Worked as Professional Services to help and provide solutions for Silicon Graphics Inc in there various PoC and demos.
- Worked with custom SGI IRIX and Linux based implementations

### **CERTIFICATIONS**

Google Cloud Platform Fundamentals: Core Infrastructure

https://www.coursera.org/account/accomplishments/certificate/8AQLYH5Z8L8R

Essential Cloud Infrastructure: Foundation

https://www.coursera.org/account/accomplishments/certificate/B36ZQYQSJKS2

Introduction to Google Cloud Platform https://verify.acloud.guru/BDA67CB8391A

Google Certified Associate Cloud Engineer 2019

https://verify.acloud.guru/D33BADCD2186

Preparing for the Google Cloud Associate Cloud Engineer Exam

https://www.coursera.org/account/accomplishments/verify/R3K5VEVNUD65

Essential Cloud Infrastructure: Core Services

https://www.coursera.org/account/accomplishments/records/GMYYPPDD38D8

## **EDUCATION**

Year 2002 - MJP Rohilkhand University, Bareilly, Uttar Pradesh Bachelor of Engineering (Computer Science)

## PERSONAL INFORMATION

Sex: Male

Date of Birth: 04th August 1979

Marital Status: Married

Languages Known: Hindi, English

Visa - Tier 2 General Dependent (Valid till April 2024)